Guide to the Paul Herman Vieth Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Paul Herman Vieth Papers
1919-1974
RG 59
Yale University Divinity School Library
3
(6 boxes)
Writings, notes, and subject files document Vieth's career as a student and professor of Religious Education at Yale. Paul Vieth was a Yale Divinity School professor in the field of Religious Education from 1931 to 1963.
Vieth, Paul H. (Paul Herman), 1895-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Paul Herman Vieth
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
1895 Born near Warrenton, Missouri
1917 B.A., Central Wesleyan College
1924 B.D., Yale Divinity School
1925 Director of research for the International Council of Religious Education; over the years he served the Council as chairman of various committees and commissions.
1928 Ph.D., Yale
1931-1939 Director of Field Work at the Yale Divinity School, Associate Professor of Religious Education
1939-1963 Horace Bushnell Professor of Christian Nurture, Yale Divinity School; under his leadership a Visual Education Service was established at YDS to serve faculty, students, and area churches.
1947-1948 Advisor on religious education with the religion division, civil information and education section of staff of General Douglas MacArthur in Japan during U.S. occupation.
1954-1955 Fulbright Scholar in Japan
1963 Professor Emeritus
1978 Died
Scope and Contents
I. Correspondence, 1929-1948.
II. Writings, Sermons, Notes, 1919-1966, n.d..
III. Working Files, n.d.
IV. PersonaI Items and Memorabilia, 1934-1974, n.d.
Paul Vieth was a pioneer in the field of Protestant religious education during the twentieth century. He is best known for his work in formulating the objectives of religious education, his leadership of the Educational Commission of the International Council of Religious Education, and his groundbreaking recognition of the value of audio-visual materials in religious education. Vieth was the first professor to offer a course in a seminary on audio-visual education.
These papers primarily document Vieth's professional career and contain relatively little personal material. The correspondence is primarily business letters related to publications. One folder contains circular letters by Vieth describing his experiences in Japan, 1947-1948. There is a fairly complete file of Vieth's writings for journals, as well as sermons, addresses, and lecture notes. The articles are primarily in typescript form, as Vieth submitted them for publication; the journal to which an article was submitted in noted on some.
The Class Notes of Series III are from Vieth's years as a student at the Yale Divinity School. They provide documentation on the content of religious education and the psychology of religion courses taught during this time period. The Working Files of Series IV were compiled for courses taught by Vieth at the Divinity School.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1929-1948
II. Writings, Sermons, Notes, 1919-1966, n.d.
III. Working Files, n.d.
IV. PersonaI Items and Memorabilia, 1934-1974, n.d.
Religious education; Educators; Vieth, Paul H. (Paul Herman), 1895-; Yale University -- Faculty
- Correspondence, 1929; Series I
  - Letters requesting permission to quote from published materials in the publication of Vieth's dissertation, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters re. writings and publications, 1930-1934 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Circular letters by Vieth from Japan; letter from Japanese friend, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Writings, Notes, Sermons, Series II
  - Articles
    - "The Purpose, History, and Promise of the International Curriculum of Religious Education"; "Statement of Progress of the International Curriculum Undertaking", 1928 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Do We Need a Superintendent?", 1933 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Time For Christian Teaching", 1933 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Is the Church a School?", 1933 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Can the Church School Build a Better Church?", 1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Education for the World Tomorrow", 1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Never Stop Learning", 1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Realizing Our Objectives Through the Christian Family", 1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "When the Church Plans for Her Children", 1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Visual Aids", 1935 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "The Projector in the Service of Christian Education", 1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "The Purpose of Teaching", 1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Education for Christlike Character", 1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Motion Pictures as an Aid to Friendship", 1936? (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Teaching the Adult Class", 1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Church Administration - For a Unified Program" in Light Bearer, 1937 Apr (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Christian Education Through the Family", 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Report on Japan" in Yale Divinity News, 1948 Nov (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Christian Education in Japan" (typescript), 1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Training Teachers to Use Audio-Visuals" in Children's Religion, 1954 Sep (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "The Superintendent at Work" in The Christian Educator, 1957 Oct (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "The Superintendent and the Teachers" in The Christian Educator, 1958 Apr (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Off to Adventure" in The Christian Educator, 1958 Jul (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Who Makes the Decision?" in The Christian Educator, 1960 Apr (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "The Pastor and the D.C.E. - a Team" in The Christian Educator, 1960 Oct (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "The General Superintendent - What is His Job?" in The Christian Educator, 1965 Jan (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Enlistment of Workers", 1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "A Job for All Seasons: Enlistment" in The Christian Educator, 1965 Apr (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "What Has Happened to Sunday Schools?" in Bethany Guide, 1965 Jun (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "How to Have Effective Workers' Conferences" in The Christian Educator, 1965 Jul (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "The General Superintendent - His Concern with Worship" in The Christian Educator, 1965 Oct (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Enlistment and Orientation of New Teachers" in The Christian Educator, 1966 Jan (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Various writings relating to period spent in Japan, 1948, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous typescript articles, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7 - 9)
  - Booklength manuscripts
    - "Report to the Sub-Committee on International Curriculum of the International Sunday School Lesson Committee", 1927 (Box 2, Folder 10a)
    - "A Critical Study of Objectives in Religious Education" (dissertation), 1928 (Box 2, Folder 10b)
    - "A Teaching Ministry for the Christian Church" (incomplete), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "The Church in its Teaching Work", 1937 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Religious Education in Japan", 1948 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Untitled ms., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Sermons and addresses
    - "The Family - the Cornerstone of Character", 1933 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - "Jesus Answers his Adversaries", 1933 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Sermon on Mt. 6:34, 1933? (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - "Commissions for Actions", 1933 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - "The Modern Religious Education Program and its Requirements in Building and Equipment", 1938 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - "The Prospect for Christianity in Japan", 1948 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - "Trends in Christian Education in the U.S", 1954 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - "Christian Education Faces the Future" - Rufus Jones Lecture, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous sermons, 1941-1956 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous sermons, 1957-1966 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous lectures, presentations, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Class notes
    - "Religious Education", "Philosophy of Education", 1919, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - "Educational Psychology", "Educational Statistics", 1922-1923 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - "New Testament Intro", 1922-1923 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - "Psychology of Religion", "Philosophy of Religion", 1922-1923 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - "Psychology of Religion", "Materials of Religious Education", 1923-1924 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - "Psychology of Religion", "Methods of Religious Education", "Elementary School Supervision", 1923-1924 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - "History of Religious Education", 1923-1924 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 26 - 28)
- Working Files, Series III
  - Curriculum
    - Introduction (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - The Meaning of Curriculum (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - History of Protestant Curriculum (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Objectives and the Curriculum (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Curriculum Principles (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Curriculum Design (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - The Learner and the Learning Process (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Utilization in the Local Church (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Study of Lesson Materials (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - The Christian Fellowship (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - The Bible in the Curriculum (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Nursery (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Kindergarten (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Primary and Junior Departments (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Memory work (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Union Seminary, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Andover-Newton, 1964-1966 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Local Church Program of Christian Education
    - History of Sunday School (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Historical (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Church as Teacher (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Education for Lay Ministry (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - Learning and Teaching (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Meaning of Religious Education (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Good Order - Discipline (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - Program of Christian Education (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - Organization for Christian Education (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - Enlistment and Training of Workers (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Outreach, Records, Measurement (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Work of the Parish Minister
    - Religion 174 - 1st semester (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - Religion 174 - 2nd semester (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - Protestant Day Schools (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - Weekday Church School (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - Vacation Church School (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Christian Education of Adults
    - Leadership (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - Education for Lay Ministry (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - Young Adult - Older Adult (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - Older Adults (Box 5, Folder 65)
    - Curriculum (Box 5, Folder 66)
    - Adults (Box 5, Folder 67)
    - Understanding Adults (Box 5, Folder 68)
    - Adult - Methods (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Religion and Public Education
    - Introduction (Box 6, Folder 70)
    - Religion and Public Education (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - Regents Prayer (Box 6, Folder 72)
    - Public School and Religion (Box 6, Folder 73)
    - Dual Enrollment / Shared Time (Box 6, Folder 74 - 75)
    - Religion in Public Education (Box 6, Folder 76)
    - Seminar on Religion and Public Education (Box 6, Folder 77)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Files re. Christian Education (Box 6, Folder 78 - 89)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1947-1964; Series IV
  - Newspaper and magazine clippings re. Vieth, 1947-1964 (Box 7, Folder 90)
  - "Paul Herman Vieth" - paper by Don Paul Gray, student at Southwestern Baptist Theological Seminary, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 90)
  - Financial material, 1934-1937 (Box 7, Folder 91)
  - Photographs from time in Japan, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 91)
  - Prints and artwork from Japan (Box 7, Folder 92)
  - Filmstrip and commentary: "In the Footsteps of Susann Lorantffy" (Box 7, Folder 93)